[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
[Music]
welcome to the stowa the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
at the knife's edge of what matters most
right now and today we are joined by
cadell last kevin orros and daniel dick
they are the authors of sex masculinity
and god
the trials this is
a unique book for me
because i've been able to
read from each of their perspectives as
they
dialogue with one another ask each other
questions
sometimes disagree and really have an
open exploration and negotiation around
these ideas
of masculinity and femininity femininity
around gender
around the future of these things and
the history
of these things and how we relate to
them as people
i'm going to start off this session by
asking a couple questions
and as questions come up for you you can
drop them in the chat
and then i will call on you to ask your
questions we'll be here for
an hour and so with that said
cadell kevin daniel thank you for being
here i really appreciate you guys
joining us at the store today
so happy to be here great to be here
tyson hello everybody
hello it's a pleasure
great all right so my first
question that i have has been like
ongoing as i've been reading this
is around the the medium itself and your
personal experience
of having these conversations and and
writing this book
and so around these topics of sex
masculinity god
what has changed for you how have you
changed what sort of
uh personal changes transformation
has happened for you around these topics
by having this kind of ongoing
conversation
i really find that when i'm reading the
book i'm brought into
like your personal experience of how
these um
things have come up in your life and how
you're grappling with them now and where
you're going with them
and so and then there's something about
this
that the the medium of having these
conversations
with other brothers with other men that
is powerful and for me i really
appreciate and aspire to that ongoing
dialogue that the three of you been
sharing so i'm curious
about your experience of the process of
writing this book
and just ways that you've changed
personally by
doing so i can
i can jump in here quick uh to
to go off that i'll let me let me just
quickly say that
it's a really good question and it's a
really deep question
for me it's kind of like i i see this
whole process of writing this book
and the ongoing trials
as almost like the third act of my
sexual existence
in my in the first act of my sexual
existence i felt as if
my sexuality was being regulated by
social categories which weren't
determined by
me so for example i didn't determine the
categories of boyfriend or girlfriend or
the normative patterns
that go into enacting those those forms
then in this and when i was doing that i
felt like
i was kind of like more robotic
if you like i was i was kind of acting
as i'm supposed to act according to a
certain social
norm then in the sort of second act of
my life
i became very individual with my
sexuality
and kind of detaching my sexuality from
what other people think or what other
people
say just to sort of figure out what i
how i connect to my sexuality
and now with this sex masculinity and
god trialogs
the way i see this as the third act is
kind of like
i'm in a mature place with myself
and i fi i'm basically trying to connect
with other people
who are open to the transformation of
identity and sexuality
as a kind of networked phenomenon if
that makes sense
where identities escape the traditional
categorization but at the same time it's
not an individual experience it's a
collective experience
so that's that's an ongoing process for
me personally and it's
really still you know early days i think
i can i can jump in here and then i'll
pass to you daniel
um i mean the inception point for this
book it's in the forward or it's in my
forward piece of the book but it is
pretty wild i'll tell the super abridged
version
um i wanted to go into phd psychology i
was studying evolutionary psychology
came across cadell in his blog and his
academic work he was doing anthropology
and then through various synchronicities
i reached out to him via email and then
i saw him by chance
chance in a cafe in santa cruz
california where i was living
and uh didn't go up to him because i was
i wasn't convinced it was him i was like
that looks like that one philosopher i
follow
years later he would reach out to me
based on a video
after i emailed him like were you at a
cafe at this time in this place and he's
like yeah i was there at a conference
and i was like
damn it and he reached out to me later
and then
life brought us together we had his
video call and just went like
hour and a half deep and we're like he's
like you need to meet this other guy
daniel he's like terence mckenna and i
was like i love terence mckenna
and then like we're just writing a book
after we start doing these trial log
series it was like very emergent
and what is most interesting about this
book is that it was spoken
um i mean i give major props to you
kiddell because cadell
in his genius organized way architected
it and structured it in the type form
but
the the speaking the act of speaking it
has a different
flavor i think than any book you'd find
where someone sat down with a blank word
processor and just started mashing you
know so
as an example you know during this as
we're
speaking and writing this book into
existence you know i think i might have
been the first one to pop but
massive life changes were happening in
accordance with the chapters
breakups movements business wins and
losses
crisis of existential magnitude you know
and then we're like working together
sharing this and then also writing the
book and it continues
we published it two months ago and we're
still in this process right now
and uh it's really incredible so i'm
grateful to be here with you all
past you daniel
yeah thank you yeah i i just have to to
uh tell the that
for me it has been like it's so this
whole transformative part of this
uh conversation because i just mentioned
that in my pre-phase that
this whole book was like symbolized by
the aurobus
the the snake that eats its tail because
on one hand we were talking about sex
that is actually something very
transformative itself
it has like the archetype of the snake
something that shapes
its old skin away and on the other hand
it's like
the force of knife and when it eats its
tail
it's because you make this full circle
which is also
on on on the cover of the book you know
which is uh leaned on on the send circle
and the gap in between so caden
we also have a lot of conversation about
the gap in the whole
whole circle but um actually
this kind of transformative reflective
dialogues that we have been drawn into
had real impact on on the personal life
so i want me to break up you know
changing job and so on one of the most
crucial things that that really stayed
kind of or that really um
were perpetually going on in in this
phase was actually the last chapter
where we talked about
death and love so what makes you
sure about what you're doing you know
and this deep questioning about
sexuality what
moves you what is ethically on what you
do
and how you proceed to gain something
meaningful out of your life and in your
relationships
and how you can measure yourself on
on your right path or not by asking
yourself
do you love it and would you do it if
you would die tomorrow
you know that's kind of like i became
more radical in that
yeah that's like the biggest change to
to be
really more radical and really enjoy
the the free fall the freefall that you
have
if you want to jump from somewhere and
if you are in love
and you just fall you know and you you
just take the courage to do it that
became more courage
like that became more radical
yeah wonderful that's really good when
you're speaking
about the space in the center of the
circle i was
um remembering a conversation about how
when we
someone was mentioning that when they
look at stars they're
typically not really looking at a star
if they do long enough they kind of lose
sight of it and
they get they look at the space between
the stars and that's also how the
the shapes and the stories and the
figures come together is through the
space in between all the stars
and i was being brought back to that
i'm we've been having a lot of
conversations here at the stoa
and about all kinds of different things
what i really appreciate about it is
that
it's sort of an embodiment of complexity
and holding many different perspectives
which is something i think you guys
strive to do in the book is
speak about all a lot of different ways
that people
relate to sexuality gender and these
polarities
and with all these conversations that
were happening
and are in is here who's been doing um a
session around
metamodern masculinity a lot of people
are involved in kind of having these
conversations um themselves
and then our central focus i think no
matter what we're talking about is
around building communitas like
connecting with one another
relating in a deeper more rich and
meaningful way
and so having these conversations what
which at times
seem quite um challenging
and by being honest as as you are and
and in my experience with others by
being honest it can allow
some chaos and confusion and ambiguity
in to the conversations and so
but you you do so in between the three
of you quite artfully and
and masterfully being articulating your
personal experiences and id
and these ideas and asking questions
that might um for some be
controversial or off limits or taboo not
to ask so i'm just
i'm curious what have been some guiding
principles for you
in how to have these conversations how
to engage
with openness and to invite openness in
others um with
just each other the three of you and
maybe with
other people as well um yeah guiding
principles
for having these these
dialogues around things that might be
taboo
in a generative and productive way
i think i think one of the crucial
notions at least for me
that has it's been a huge process of
discovery
which is always ongoing which is
to be aware of the way in which you're
unconsciously identifying
yourself with certain ideas so
if you're unconsciously identifying
yourself with certain ideas i feel like
if someone critiques or disagrees with
you
you can sort of take it too personally
and then it sort of becomes it becomes
too
emotionally charged and you lose
you lose sight of what is really being
discussed
or even what the disagreement is about
so you know i think one of the first
moves is this ability to realize that
your intellect
serves the way in which you're
unconsciously identifying
and for me you know i like in the past i
would unconsciously identify
too much as a certain type of academic
and i would reify my identity around
that too much
and i think releasing myself from that
gives me the
the freedom to basically interact with
anyone about
almost anything if i'm not too much
clinging to any one idea as too much
identified with myself then the second
principle
is to be aware that the very
form of the discourse like the very form
of the discursive arena
changes the nature of what can be
discussed so one of the biggest things
for me
is that when i was in academia i was in
a very interdisciplinary environment
that where in principle you could talk
about anything
but i found that what was implicit in
the academic structure was a type of
modality of professorship where
the discourse was shaped all around that
one professor's ideas
so in reality we couldn't talk about
anything we could only talk about the
paradigm
accepted by that professor so in that
sense
even though that an interdisciplinary
environment i felt personally
that topics of sexuality topics of
masculinity and topics of religion
were off were off topic you you couldn't
really go
deep into those topics of sex
masculinity and god
so that's really why i found and tried
to network with kevin and daniel
because i was searching for spaces to go
deep into those topics and i wanted i
didn't want to have any censorship
i didn't want to have any
pre-conceptualization
to change the way i want to approach
those ideas
and so i think that's that's that's
really the way i would
approach that and i'll throw it to you
kev
yeah brilliant i love that i've had a
similar experience
i didn't even make it to grad school but
on my way i had a very similar
sense working in graduate student
laboratories
and for me the guiding principles tyson
i love these questions
really revolve around some notions i
have about reality itself which is
language is a bleeding edge
language is a multi-dimensional
template whatever that means like
multi-dimensional
doesn't have to mean you know quantum
physics it just means
language is a type of
magic it's a type of structuring
principle or scaffolding onto which
culture itself
is built so if that's the case which i
believe it is
then we can only evolve as fast as our
language
the breadth and width and depth of our
conversations are going to determine the
level we can
heal connect and build a new
civilization which is
pretty obviously here in 2020 what we
kind of need to do
and i see some of the biggest divides
around the taboos
especially between the masculine
feminine and sexuality
and around god itself and the the notion
of god
right and this this is part and parcel
of the issue
of the whole idea of censorship or
taboos in general it's like let's not
talk about or
language these things let's not
categorize these things because
we don't know what to do with them
that's what i'm that's what i hear
culture say when it creates a taboo
so obviously the role of a philosopher
and i self-style self-identifies
philosopher
i believe daniel and kadel do as well
the philosopher
who's a lover of wisdom their role in
the society is actually to bring these
things
up create context create culture and
create conversations around them so we
kind of chose three titanic type
taboos to do this in and quickly some of
the other guiding principles
definitely iron sharpens iron so what's
unique about these conversations
is that we we don't agree on a lot of
things
later we might agree and come to a level
where like oh i really see your
perspective it actually gels with my
perspective but in the beginning
we were we were you know just giving out
ideas and maybe disagreeing maybe
changing or shifting perspective
so um healthy competition a more of a
martial artist or dojo style of iron
sharpens iron
if i can speak something at the limit of
my understanding to you
and like as cadell was describing you
don't become emotionally compromised and
you can speak back your response
at the edge of your understanding we
both grow in our knowledge and our
gnosis
and so that's an incredible part of this
dialogue and what's really unique is
unlike a dialogue or a dyad
a dyad tends to reach a stability or an
energetic where there isn't a lot of
room because it's just
like think like ping pong in the triad
in the structure of a triangle
it creates a very unique third chaotic
element which actually
most of our trilogues and most of the
chapters of the book the territory we
end up
in with our ideation is so far afield
and so much more potent than what we
created in the structure
so there's an emergent property of it
that is incredible
i'll pass to you daniel
thank you yeah i can just underline
everything what is said so far
and there's on the line the appreciation
that we have been
able to talk that freely together and
and bring this out because
i was pursuing a phd which uh i now also
dropped it because the frameworks of
academia have been like
too tight for me and to have this
conversation with carol and kevin
was just relieving was you know
because i could combine different
notions of investigation
in one hand you have like the analytic
investigation
that i appreciate very much where you
scrutinize oneself
on the other hand you have the
metaphorical
investigation that opens up your mind
into
patterns so you see similar patterns
all over which is very much from one
field that i also appreciate very much
as system science
so you try to find similar patterns
all over uh different aspects or
different
well in system science you call them
systems you know
and one thing that always is interesting
about
language and taboos
is that when you talk about a
taboo it's not taboo anymore
you know so there is something very
unique about talking about
what is hidden talking about what is
sacred
because what is sacred is the same
as taboo and what is taken what is taboo
you actually don't touch you don't talk
about it
why is that so because in this is the
most
initial core of our in our driving
is that what we want to reach for and
that is something very unconscious
usually
it can be sex it can be gone but it
drives you to to really
focus on something without knowing
what it is in this black box because
it's taboo because it's sacred
because you don't talk about it so once
you talk about it
you bring it to the light you bring it
to the transparent and you change it
so the biggest thing about talking about
taboo
and talking about sex talking about god
and be kind of heretic to that
it's the willingness to change
because it will change you and that's
what happened so much into
in in this conversations too you know it
is
it is a mechanism itself that you also
find in psychotherapy and stuff like
that
but if you bring it to that level it
brings you massive changes because
you have to question a lot if you
question these
kind of so intrinsic
taboo topics
and yeah i think that that's like
the most crucial part if you want to
really focus
on this conversations that bring you
a way of change that you are progressing
in your self-development
that you're open to to make yourself
change
you know that you are open to discovery
what is
what is the hidden behind the hidden
to to reveal that will change you and
you have to have the willingness
to do that yeah
really good thank you well alex s
question is pointing in the direction
that i was going to go next so i'm just
going to invite alex
to unmute and ask a question if you'd
like alex
alex s do you hear me
yeah i can hear you can you hear me now
twice yep heard that
great thanks excuse me um
yeah thanks to all the speakers uh i
think this is a really important
uh topic to be discussing um
i found in my own experience so i'm in
my 30s
um just a lot of confusion you know
uh coming of age and not really uh
having a clear sense of what it means to
be a man
what masculinity actually is supposed to
be and
you know all kinds of models from my
past you know parents
family members etc that don't really fit
with present reality
um and also you know whenever i've
gone out and tried to uh get some advice
just getting a lot of blank stares in
response you know you ask a man
you know uh you know somebody in my
family let's say well what is a man
and what do you do you know should you
get married should you not
um and not really getting clear answers
to those questions
uh or really a kind of a guidance for
how do you find out
you know how do you make these decisions
for yourself
and uh so my question is um
so i appreciate you know the need to be
in discussion
and to be uh inquiring and i'm wondering
if you've arrived at any kind of um
uh maybe a sense of what the meaning of
masculinity
is in our time you know you mentioned uh
it's a post-religious age we live in
it's a uh it's an age of post-feminism
and
a lot of sexual uh changes have happened
um and i'm wondering if you have any
sense you know what is the meaning of
masculinity for us today
uh is there such a thing are there any
um maybe like points or moments or
aspects of that
that we can talk about you know what is
a man in our world
thanks thanks for the question alex and
i think it's really well framed
and really thought out and i really feel
i really feel the emotion
behind your your question and it's and
it's an emotion that i i share
i share with you in the in the
conversation
in some of the conversations we've had
specifically about
um gender archetypes and in some of the
conversations we specifically had about
um masculine movements i can i can open
um sort of how we've approached this
this question that you're posing which
is that
in the past before the modern period
um man and woman were seen to be
eternal essences they were seen to be
um you know it would be impossible for
someone in the 15th century
to question their gender identity
it was the essence of their being it it
wasn't something where there's a
reflective distance
of course that all changes in the modern
world
and that largely changes because
the whole traditional structure um
kind of gets divided from within where
in the traditional world there's a
there's a distinction between the public
sphere and the private sphere
and in the modern world that distinction
is
kind of annihilated in in some sense
everyone is now in the public sphere and
i don't think anyone would say that that
move is ethically wrong i think that
everyone should be
fully in the public sphere and everyone
should be
fully able to express and perform and
act in the public sphere
nonetheless the question of what that
means for contemporary masculinity is
something
that i think we've barely begun to
scratch the surface of so
let me quickly say that what i see in
contemporary masculine movements
is a type of strange um
inner identity tension between
and this can be seen in for example the
red pill community
and this this this inner tension is
between
the man who wants to enact the
traditional life
of 50 years ago
and the man who wants to just um
give in to his base level evolutionary
impulses so
the man who just wants to enact the old
traditional scaffolding is basically
looking for some
order looking for some symbolic
certainty that would allow him to
contain his sexual energy
whereas the man who's just acting on his
evolutionary impulses
is basically saying no conceptualization
scheme works i'm just going to do
what is natural to my body and
from my point of view both are dead end
and what i would offer as a potential
third way
and this is a third way that i'm trying
to work out in myself
it's not a it's not something that i
have a final answer for
but that third way is trying to connect
deeply with the real of my evolutionary
impulse
not to deny it to accept that that's in
my body and that's
that's a part of me and that's strong
energy but
second to connect that energy
to a higher communal ideal of leadership
so for me personally what masculinity
would be able to do
is authentically connect with their
sexual energy
and then and then sublimate that energy
to a new communal ideal of leadership
but that new communal ideal of
leadership would of course take a much
different form in the networked
age in the networked age look at what
we're doing right now this is this is a
digital network
none of us are connected in physical
reality nonetheless i hope
in my speech i'm bringing a type of you
know masculine type of leadership
through sublimation and that does good
for the men and women
who are in my network so that would be
my first
start to the answer and i'll pass it to
you kev
yeah i love what you said there i mean
there's a part of me that will pull kind
of an alan watts here and it's like
you know this is like water asking why
it's wet
if you're a man asking what masculinity
is it's like
there's a part of me that just wants to
point out the absurdity of it
because in a way masculinity
is is like it's like the suchness if
you're in a male body you know
you're you're masculine on one level and
obviously there's so many shades now
and gradients and i obviously
experienced those as well
so that being said you know the reason
this question is being asked i
imagine and the reason i feel like
masculinity is in crisis and confusion
and i can feel even in my body right now
like a little bit of the the anger and
like
despair that this is a problem in our
age
and like i i've experienced it and which
all of that
energy is why i've followed this path
which has led me to this call
and writing this book with these two
gentlemen we've lost rites of passage
we've lost the rituals of initiation and
we've lost
positive male mentors and elders who
contextualize
and create the positive masculine
imago image role for boys
to come into
and and just and you don't need to like
do an exhaustive anthropological study
on this merely look to the masculine
role models
produced by western culture toxic
images of machismo psychopathy
abuse i mean even the most watered-down
ones think about the hardcore like tv
cop or like the action hero in hollywood
they they exude a lot of alpha male
positive leadership
qualities provision protection
providence these are these are
part and parcel of the masculine essence
however
the heart emotional intelligence
treating women and children with respect
leading the tribe to some total zero
game goals
as masculine leaders and role models
co-creating
with a tribe or village is absent
because this individual
lone wolf be with as many women as you
can make as much money as you can you
know i don't need to give you the litany
of the toxic male images and metoo has
awakened this to the whole collective
in a way that's very unique in our
network day it just cadel was pointing
out so it's quite incredible
now what what do i think that
masculinity means in a post-religious
post-feminist world
it's gonna look like think of the most
grounded integrated man you've known in
your life
and just start to intuit and feel the
qualities he possessed
how did he treat younger males how did
he treat
other powerful men what were his actions
and his words were they in alignment and
integrity in the communal sphere
and he brought up a great point of
delineation cadell between the public
and private
sphere we've had public figures and
public men leading
our civilization but in their private
sphere and now with the internet
we're finding out it was a [ __ ] show for
a lot of these men
riddled with addiction and abuse so
a true image of masculinity and again
this is a working hypothesis
i'm trying to enact this with my own
struggles and foibles
is a man that is uniting those together
is not afraid to to take off his armor
and admit that he needs help
the age of the lone wolf is dead
what we need are men who are embodying a
life-giving
archetype of masculinity and that's why
i think part of the impulse for this
book is much of our culture worships
death it's a death culture and a lot of
the masculine figures
although they look real shiny on the
podium with their suit and tie
death culture is what is propping them
up so
the ultimate thing is like if a man is
going to embody true masculinity
it must be life-giving for the culture
for the for the whole
and i'll leave it there
beautiful words in here strong words
um what is the masculinity today
i mean we have pointed out now a bit the
problems that
led to this uh question
in which uncertainty has been all over
in identity of masculinity as well as
in other areas of our world
and that was
one of the questions why we assume one
of the issues why we wrote this book
to give some orientation about this
question
which we kind of also let it open
on one hand it is important to
have the firm masculinity that is
opposing
uh femininity so we had talked about so
the oneness that you create in relation
to a feminine so i think
that is one path that is very crucial
and needs
a firm balance and this balance
is not something that is firm
for itself but is in relation
to the feminine so how you can make a
compliment
on a healthy way to the famine being a
masculine
and the other way is really finding this
complementarity
in yourself where you are not
searching for the one to become the one
with someone else but where you try to
become
in yourself completed fulfilled realized
where you also can embrace in yourself
as well as masculine as a feminine
energies so that is something i
i don't agree fully with kevin i see it
both ways are very important
so one hand what kevin is saying about
we need strong man let's stay
and here is to agree to cadel we need
this positive
way of man that know what they can
that know what they want i think
this leadership type of math is needed
with some new connotations which is
something more feminine like
being a lot of in communication that
allows this network
of self-determined individuals
and and by doing that i see also the
possibility that there is like
a balance in yourself but always
in relation to someone else that you
also can perceive as
someone as one you know
the question is really what is what is
the lack
in yourself that you perceive
that you might want to fulfill with
someone else
and this lag is also kind of what what
drives you
or that drives you unconscious
and in in your relationships when you
learn to start to really
uh see someone else that you love
actually
and you finding out oh what you love
about the other person is
actually something that i would like to
love about myself
you know and if you see this continuous
process issue of self-development of
self-discovery
where you can find actually your
strength
to see that is what i can that is what i
want and this is what i stand for
then this is a proper collaboration in a
network possible
where there is not blaming where that's
not
the power mechanism where you can
respect mutually and same equally to
each other
could be a man or a woman doesn't matter
but
i think this self-development is is
quite crucial and the the real question
about the masculinity
is how did how did we
get into this uncertainty and
how does it really help us to
to jump into this uncertainty to to ask
ourselves
what is what we want for from oneself
what is what we want for our community
i think that the uncertainty it's a
great blessing
that we are drawn into individually
on gender on identity as well as on the
state of the world
because it initiates the change it
is the first step to to a new path
and and i think we need to definitely
and for for a healthy
outcome out of that is really looking
first
inside of oneself and discover
what is the lack what is where is
not the love and the compassion for
oneself
you know where do we try to find it
somewhere else
where do we try to find security in
something else
where do we try to find leadership in
someone else
where do we try to find love from
so i do think that these things are
crucial for community life
but how we can stand on the ground that
we can give that
ourselves first so we are not acting out
of a lack
but out of abundance
awesome fiona daniel is
touching i think around your question
now so i'm wondering if you want to ask
your question or
follow up um with where your question is
at now considering
daniel's comments sure um
i was wondering what i mean we've talked
a lot about this being a post-feminist
era but
feminism is obviously an ongoing
philosophy and
movement what could do differently to
create space for
the development of masculinity and you
know
a safe space for masculinity to grow
i can i can uh i can take that because i
have
something of a history with engagement
with
academic feminism for the past 10 years
i remember when i started college
i was in a community college and one of
the
one of the courses they offered was
gender studies but
when i was taking the course what was
obvious was that
it wasn't really gender studies it was
it was really it was really women's
studies
and it was viewing gender from
basically from the perspective of
femininity
so and i've seen that be a problem
that's gone on now for a while so
my basic answer to your question i hope
this is
i hope this is precise and simple
which is that for me
if feminism is going to make room for
matt
from masculinity to really think through
itself in a new way
then we need to we need to structure
gender studies
around the idea of positive tension
between masculine and feminine energies
tension between masculine and feminine
energies is
really important and
if we don't balance the tension between
masculine and feminine energies
we either get masculine domination
or feminine domination and neither
serves the whole so i think
paradoxically
in order to serve the whole we need to
understand the tension between the two
and from that perspective
we can reinvent each other in a ongoing
symbiosis with each other because if the
feminine changes
then the masculine will change and if
the masculine changes
the feminine will change and we need a
space that can contain that tension
and i think that that would be very
interesting to see
but then i'll share that with you kevin
that's all i have to say on that topic
yeah this is this is very interesting
and this comes up a lot in my
my profession i'm a i'm a coach for
entrepreneurs
and i do emotional integration work
archetypal
shadow work as well and a lot of my
clients are really powerful
women in business and this is a number
one question they ask
is like how can we support men to heal
and integrate right because
um in some of the circles i've run in
maybe
the conscious community the health and
wellness community whatever you want to
call it
the women have been doing their work
longer they've been gathering doing red
tent
doing doing ceremony doing deep healing
and interpersonal work and the men now
are really rising and i see the last
decade and really the last couple years
to really see
more and more groups activate and
activate i think mankind project was
been holding it down
but there's so many new groups doing
this and a big part of that is
you know the taboo around men showing
any kind of emotion
any kind of vulnerability at all walks
of life right from your working class
firefighter police officer but even
you know the male yoga teacher or the
male corporate gentleman you know
those taboos are finally breaking down
and there's finally enough context
and healing momentum
that i think we can start to have those
circles emerge more and more and more
now so the question of the direct
relationship
um this one's tough because it addresses
one of the biggest shadows between
masculine feminine which is the shadow
of codependency
and so if the woman is unwilling to
detach from the man's process
not try to be his therapist but also
simultaneously without
emasculating him or causing any female
deferment or all these other things that
have been
identified um allowing him and
to courageously do his work even if it
involves dissolution and
really painful ego annihilation which it
often does
and in the same way if the woman's doing
her work
and is connecting with other sisters and
powering up
and clearing some of her trauma which
you know one in three women have like
serious sexual trauma i mean this is a
this is a systemic thing that touches
all of us
in the same way that man has to avoid
becoming her therapist
and demeaning controlling trying to fix
trying to rush in with problem solving
so that the very relationship between
masculine and feminine at the core
one-on-one level is a microcosm of the
men and women's work that has to happen
and gets to happen
so the very simple way to support it
either way
is to support it and not to meddle
and understand even though your
intentions are good that you know
there's some things that men can only do
with other men
and vice versa there's some things that
women can only do with other women
and i think one of the most dangerous
things is this blurring
and you know it's not i don't want to
say it's transgenderism because
that's not what it is but this whole
idea that gender is just
a role or it doesn't matter and you know
the men and women's exclusion is a bad
idea
i don't agree with that at all just from
personal experience you know all
philosophy and concept
aside so yeah i really look forward to
more
women whether they feel like they're in
the feminism strain
or not and more men even if they're in
more traditional
alpha male roles to start to realize the
importance of this work and
to actually support one another even if
it's at a distance
so i'll leave it there for you daniel
thank you there have been so many
questions coming up here
on the right side and so beautifully
framed uh i just wanna i mean
there is a lot to talk about in here so
it makes difficult to recap all the
questions that are already here
and the first question that has been uh
asked to
to make this round fully um but
i want to make some some comment about
durkheim
um about the sacred and the profane that
was asked because um
it touches several questions that has
been asked here
too including the first question
what is what is the spaces that we need
and here comes is a kind of a paradox
where we hold attention
it is we need a sacred space
for the transformation
so the sacred it's like the unification
it's what we are drawn into
the sacred space is an empty space
too because it can allow things to
happen
so one of the crucial things that we
need
is just give yourself the time
you know where you don't have to do
something
give allow yourself just to be and that
brings up as a lot of things especially
if you make it to something
sacred it's because it's special to you
it's like the first act of
self-compassion
the second is that when we
when we uh unify in something
sacred it's um
it is because we really care on one hand
if we have something that we
want to change about ourselves
and we we talk about the most sacred
that's
that's on our self it is something that
we can talk about sex we can talk about
our most intimate relationship and as
sad
it changes
and when when it comes to say
um what is
what is really crucial about
masculinity and what do we
bring to ourselves and to to the
compassion
that we can make out of the sacred
spaces
i believe that everybody brings
something on the table
and everybody is kind of different and
what he
can really offer
and everybody has something that that is
really
unique to him and this is actually
the most sacred point where you where
you can reach
but to discover this and to hold spaces
for that
it's like the second sacred space loop
in which you can just unfold and detach
of everything that you thought about
that you have to
and and this makes you like the king
in in the archetype we say that's what i
want
you know all that makes you the magician
that says
this is to create this is the reality
that i create
but i do believe that especially in
our times in our civilization that we
are
right now we can create time
and this is something so crucial like
you have the time
you don't have to hurry from one thing
to the other
you have to take your time for yourself
this is the very first
act of self-compassion that leads you
to discover yourself and
and to and people like kevin
that do these coachings you know or that
you take the time
to listen to these podcasts you know is
actually
already the first step that you care
about yourself
and yeah i think these are
already steps but the ultimate step is
when you become
the creator of your reality you become
the creator
of what is intrinsic unique to you when
you become the
the architect that you want to be that
you become the author that you want to
be
and so on but the beauty about it
is where do you find the spaces where
you can co-create
with such individuals on this level
you know and i'm really glad i found
cameron cadell
on that path you know to be a part of a
co-creation where you're just standing
in your truth
and you're making your part what you
doing best
and to to get into
another round of of it's not only about
the individual it is
how to collaborate how to communicate
this is our network
area how do how do we can be free
from any change of thoughts to create
something
meaningful and how do we
manage this to do this is i think the
next step that i'm really intrigued to
to see in stuff like small villages or
self-determined communities and stuff
like that also to
put on uh one question was like do we
going for
tribal community masculinity i think the
network
like the digital nomadism or digital
local community that has notions of
tribal
is bringing this to a full circle what i
can see is in the future
where you are actually very linked to
the nature
and to permaculture stuff or really
touching nature as well as
your sex as as your nature but you also
can be
highly connected through the digital age
and network
through the global spirit of united
humanity
but in in between is the
self-development of doing that
and this is going to be still a long
walk to do
together but i think here are pioneering
ideas
and they show strong individuals that
that have the courage to walk this path
of self-determination
that is what really meant the the
enlightenment to really say
we're we are not bowed to to
anything but our our our mind
and we really want to do something out
of
not because someone is telling us but
because we want it
that was the initial part of democracy
but i think
we're now able to do that on because of
the technological level
but on a physical and psychological
emotional and mental level
we're still lacking very much behind to
really ask us the question
do we really doing what we want
yeah because it's hard you know
yeah i give it to you to all these other
questions ah
yeah this is really good and the
questions are going off in the comments
um do you guys want to do would you like
to stay
and answer a couple more questions or
should we wrap up here for us there's
for me there's no time limit we can keep
going
okay well i would like to invite aaron
to and that's good with you as well
daniel i see kevin's got a thumbs up
um i want to go to rn with where your
question is at
now um i think daniel touched on it a
bit and then invite levi
as well to then um take in because you
your
questions circle around a similar thing
so then if levi wants to take in and
just um build on that i think that would
be good so aaron will you
um go ahead and ask your question yeah
thanks tyson uh thanks guys for being
here this is really awesome
i i really can sense this conversation
could keep
going i want to know more i want to talk
to you guys more um
but yeah my question is that uh it
sounds to me as if you're championing
a uh tribal communal masculinity like
returning to sort of the
collective networked masculinity um
it also sounds like your champion um
championing like
sexual self-discovery and liberation um
and since men naturally compete over
women sort of in tribal setting
do you guys also champion traditional
monogamy
and um or something else and do you
see some sort of uh sexual regulation
that needs to be imposed
if you're going to have a tribal way of
life
for men you might say
thanks so much for your question aaron i
i
i love this question i i it's it's a
question that has
it occupies so much of my mind um i have
my per my personal view is that one of
the reasons
why marxism was so so much of a failure
and one of the reasons why practical
communist
politics is so ineffective
is because they don't have an adequate
theory
of human psyche and sociosexual
development
and one of the biggest
roadblocks to authentic communism of
communal
style of living is of course that
our sublimations fall in a stable
pattern within
what we call the nuclear family between
a man and a woman
raising children and overcoming that as
a stable
erotic geometry or a stable life
geometry
is to me the biggest possible challenge
you
you could think so i don't have i don't
have
concrete um answers
but what i can say is that
whatever our sexual nature it
does not fall into a stable category
meaning if you say polyamory if you say
monogamy if you say whatever category
you use
our sexuality does not fit neatly into a
category
it rebels against any mental
abstractions of this nature
and that makes it extremely chaotic
and that makes it extremely emotionally
intensely disturbing
and most of our identities vis-a-vis
sexuality
are in my view reaction formations
against the chaos of this fact
to give some stability to give some
mental coherence
to the intrinsic chaos of this energy
how this now now what we can say
concretely
is that this energy does find some
stability in
what we call the nuclear family
precisely because
man and woman are linked by the child
now man and woman being linked by the
child
is i think
in this sense one of the most authentic
sublimations that you can give your life
to
because i had a conversation for example
with
um with one of my phd colleagues who
wrote a book and he has many and he has
children
and he was we're just remarking over how
much more complex and how much more real
his children
seem to him than his books or his phd
thesis
so there's a way in which our cultural
sublimations
pale in comparison to our biological
sublimations of actually having a child
so if my here's my final here's my final
thought on this on this problem is if
you're going to have
a transcendence to a higher order level
of social being in a communal setting
you have to treat very carefully how
these relations
are synergistically coherent with
reproduction if you don't figure out how
the synergies are coherent with
reproduction
it will it will be a nightmare and it
will fall apart and it will disintegrate
so that to me is one of the biggest
horizons for thinking today and
contemporary philosophy
i'll quickly give my my two pins here um
i agree with cadell this is the most
problematic
um situation in communal environments
and having lived on eco villages and
talked to a lot of people creating them
even here in bali talking to people
creating them
the number the number one and two things
that destroy intentional communities are
sex and money
which relate to power obviously the
third hidden one
and the sexuality one it's like we've
been so repressed
in the christian west there's so much
taboo
um things like you know the sexual
revolution polyamory
swinging all these these deviant you
know again
because of the repression modalities i
think have emerged out of that
um and to your first point erin i think
this is a great question
um the communal tribally linked
masculine is the strongest masculine in
my
opinion the isolated masculine and the
corporate high-rise on wall street or
the isolated masculine in the suburbs
is a very weak form and i think there's
a lot of evidence for that
now in a healthy tribal communal dynamic
and by healthy i mean
there are clear agreements there are
clear shared goals and values
there's some form and it doesn't have to
be religious but there's some form it
can be musical
it can be revelatory it can be
initiatory it can be psychedelic
there's a lot of different ways to
create communitas that actually work
they're all ancient i think there's some
modern spends we can obviously do with
tech and all the things we've learned we
can bring it all forward
i'm not proposing we go back to archaic
structures and just like
you know live in loincloths they tried
that in the 60s it was a nightmare
we can integrate and go forward and the
communal the communal tribe
collective and again this is this is a
sense i have i haven't
ever i would think fully experienced it
and maybe
it does exist somewhere i hear good
things about tamara and portugal i don't
know if any of you are familiar with
that community has a really long running
track record
but the the issues of sexual competition
with men and women would be non-issues
as nullified by the communitas field
where if the whole village is presencing
it
and there is communication even if
so-and-so is sleeping with so and so and
this person wanted to and like
you know all that stuff's just going to
exist you know we're tribal we're apes
we're gods and we're apes it's going to
be there but i believe it can be
dealt with in a good way that doesn't
create
you know a game where people lose i
think
it can create a game where there's
maturation and growth
and this is again elders if there are
elder men that hold business
of power and are properly respected
their their like
mediation and ability to navigate these
spaces is
critical if it's a bunch of young 20
alpha males that are in
that are basically 12 year old boys in
puberty and
strong masculine bodies yeah it's going
to turn into orgies it's going to turn
into violence
so if you have the intergenerational
dialogue if you have communitas
if you have agreements and collective
value systems i believe it's it's
navigateable
and that's a belief so i'm trusting
that's the case
before before you pick up daniel i just
wanted to
uh quickly say also about this uh what
kevin said about the win-loss dynamic
that if someone gets sex someone else
views that they don't get sex
like if some like if like if if you
if you have sex with someone someone
else can feel as if
you were attacking them or as someone
was something was taken away from me
because they because they had sex this
is because
the second positive sum yeah
yeah we can't it's hard to view sex in a
positive sum frame basically
because because sex is one a super
enjoyable energy
and two of a feeling that we
it's scarce a feeling that it's lacking
so when you combine this
the extreme enjoyment from sexuality and
the perception of lack of sexuality
it gets hyper valued so the only way in
which that could be reduced
is if there was an authentic sublimation
where that same level enjoyment is
produced
inside the individual and the only
experience i know that can do that
is the psychedelic experience so
if psychedelic experience was a part of
the community would that change the way
we discuss sexuality
i don't know that's a possibility but
i'll give that to you daniel sorry for
taking over
thank you very good thoughts still um
to i'm always the last one in the round
and that's what is my my aim is always
to to bridge kevin and cadell and
put my synchronicities into that that is
always always my
my role and my position where i find
myself i also very confident in that
but sometimes it's hard because i have
so many thoughts on that
but um what i can say from here is um
i do think that we're gonna have
a cultural change on the nuclear
nuclear family that's not especially in
those
that are still in this process where the
man makes
the money and the woman takes care about
the children
but we have other cultures where this um
this polarity has has changed into a
multiplicity
we are right now with the with the
uncertainty on how we're going to
proceed on that
and if it comes about a tribal community
or digital networking
person that is highly linked with
everybody
or if it's someone in in the city where
you have the multiplicity of
possible relationships to to find
yourself your sexuality and so on
it becomes uh quite
disturbing and and the need for some
stability
is on the stake what i believe is that
the desire that drives
sex and power
is one of the challenges that we have to
not
look outside of ourselves but inside of
ourselves if we
find desire in
in the sex and in in power about making
money
it's because it is the driving force
of of change and
if we get stuck in it we also get stuck
in our self-development
that is why i appreciate on one hand
to have an intimate relationship
where you can actually see someone else
with all the love and have the sexual
pleasure
but i also see that um as something that
is not permanent that
can be permanent but uh
as soon as you reach a point
where you change yourself that much
that the attraction that the other
person
gives to you is not something anymore
that you feel
as something desirable
then you change yourself
and if the relationship changes with you
that is for me the most beautiful
outcome that you can have
so the relationship continues and there
is continuous growth
paralleled what i see is
with the multiplicity is that this
changes or the possibility to change or
not
to to go through big changes of one
person
is that breaks up are more often
which could be repaired more easily in
smaller communities because there is not
much
of the multiplicity to get there but on
the other hand
i feel really if you just step
back from um
from this is this is just love or this
is just sex or this is just
unconscious desire that driving me but
if you put yourself
into a a reflective mode
in a mature consciousness about your
relationship
and your community you can take it
always as something to grow from
and that should be if you stick together
in a relationship or not
it doesn't matter what i did find out
that
if you have like a lot of
different sexual uh intercourses with
everybody that disturbs a lot
uh every kind of of progress
you just get scattered instead of
getting
into one and it's kind of just to the
the other persons
so i didn't think that
that this is like i mean if you would
have like one person
a week sex every day someone else
i didn't think that is really healthy i
mean i've also
done this and i couldn't recommend it
but um to to go really deep
into a trusting uh relationship
where you can hold spaces for each other
it's something very meaningful
but you don't have to get also in the
trap to be the third point of someone
else
you know but just see okay that's that's
me that's my growth
you know and i do believe that
when you go into different phases
of learning of changing yourself
you know you just become your desires
become less
because you already got it you know
if you really followed like naturally
okay i have this desire to have this
sexual intercourse or
this kind of powers and so on
i mean there's the shortcut to say well
i
i don't have these desires you know just
happy as i am
but there is also like the long way of
saying well i want to follow this
desires
to feel complete and then you're going
to figure out that
another desire will come up you know
and i also see that as something very
meaningful to follow
because otherwise you suppress it
so i also um would say
follow your dreams follow your desires
but
at some point the desires
become less and you really ask yourself
what is what is meaningful behind all of
that
and and there i'm i'm i'm more into
into this buddhist perspective where
like the happiness is like really here
now
and as soon as you have a desire your
mind and your emotion goes into the
future
which is not something that exists
and and happiness you find just in here
now
but to make this flow happy you know and
coherent with your life it's a free fall
because you don't know what's coming
next
just uh accepting it more and more
so for all the persons that
i mean there is a lot of unhealthy
sexuality too
and i do think that it is useful to have
some regulations
for these but to have
spaces for for everyone but in in the
course of how you develop yourself
your desires changes and i do
see that the desires
have also a certain arrow which
which is to realize oneself completely
as
something that is one we don't lack
anymore
but you become real
of your full potential which is like
being the one
yeah i'll leave it like this for for now
so many excellent kevin you have a
question would you
unmute and ask your question
oh me hi i'm always see hold on we find
it
um yeah um
so chapter two of your book is something
about uh
the history of archetypes and i know
kevin you
all oh i just realized my background is
a bug i
totally didn't realize that sorry um
and uh alec bug i know right
um and kevin you sort of
paint yourself as you use the word
archetypal to describe yourself
um i'm wondering what the role of the
framework of archetypes
um plays in your respective analyses and
understanding and in your trial log
and could you give some examples of say
how different archetypes
have manifested themselves in the modern
world
um where they're lacking and where they
can be improved or what kind of new
archetypes we should be striving for if
that's the right way to word the
question
thank you okay so this is
this is one of the topics where kevin
daniel and i i think
have disagreements so this question of
of archetypes so all safe i'll say for
me
i'm i'm kind of as i understand the
jungian concept of archetypes
it's that the archetype say for example
the wise king
or the divine queen or you know the
divine feminine the divine masculine
these are kind of reified as eternal
essences
that we discover in the collective
unconscious
and for me i don't really think
archetypes function in that way
i think archetypes are basically
ideas that emerged in evolution
and that those ideas reflect
a type of evolutionary strategy
in relationship to evolutionary
constraints so for example
you could imagine primates very much
like humans
evolving in language self-consciousness
that whole thing
happens and then you know conscious
entities find themselves
in sexuated biological bodies and they
come up with
two ideas which kind of cover the field
of you know one body seems to be
stronger it doesn't have the capacity to
reproduce
uh has whatever more more muscle mass so
it's
suited for certain functions another
body is
shorter it has the capacity to reproduce
and so forth so it's going to get
filtered into these functions
and that these get reified through
different different historical epochs
i think that the crucial dimension in my
analysis
is the asymmetry in the archetypes
in the modern period because women are
collectively wanting to come into the
traditionally male
field but it's not really the opposite
way
and and that's biologically determined
to the degree that
men can't men men biologically can't
reproduce
like men are biologically unable to
really
embody that function whereas it's not
true the other way around
so to me what this asymmetry in the
archetype suggests
is that these archetypes have nothing to
do with eternity
what i mean here is that both to me
here's the difficult thing to think
how can we think the asymmetry in the
archetypes and the way in which they'll
be historically transcended for
something totally different
and i think that that historical
transcen transcendence to something
totally different
involves the way in which our identities
get wrapped up between man woman and
child
so in some sense i think this
internalization of man woman and child
internal to each individual is where
we'll find new archetypes
but i i don't know yet how that will
manifest of course in our current
universe i think we see many archetypes
of superheroes all sorts of action
figures many different virtual figures
in like world of warcraft or
you know there's all sorts of ways in
which
consciousness plays with its body in a
virtual avatar form
and that's where i try to think what is
the future of the virtual avatar
visa vr body
i'll pass that to you kevin
yeah i love this question kevin and not
just because we have the same name
um i think i fall much more into the
jungian
camp and maybe the more psycho spiritual
domain
on the teleology i do believe archetypes
i mean i don't know i wouldn't claim
that they're some kind of eternal
blueprint like plato's forms or
something although i think that's an
elegant way to talk about it
but they do seem to be psychic dominance
that are older than humanity itself
and so when you analyze collective
dreams and you analyze the myths of the
world especially the creation myths
when you analyze and just look at
all the different ways humans have used
animals
symbols story man and woman
god and demon there's all these
interesting archetypes
usually conveyed through symbol and
story that are
ubiquitous and so how do these manifest
in our life
well they manifest in huge ways when you
have eyes to see
and so i find that as a man
archetypes can be extremely empowering
there's also a shadow side of being
possessed by an archetype and
grandiosity which is one of the
great trials for many men and their ego
is falling into grandiosity which i
certainly in the past have
guilty of um women also with these
life-giving feminine
earth archetypes there's a very powerful
pathway of empowerment there's also a
pathway of disempowerment and
dissolution of a personality
fit for a relationship or a personality
that's healthy and integrated
in a society and is contributing so
the way i characterize archetypes is
really like
when you are embodying your best self
and we can all
have a reference point for this right
like you can just imagine right now
let's just use the sexual space you were
looking your best
feeling your best you said all the right
things you legitimately felt like a
charismatic
badass sexy [ __ ] you know
whatever your orientation is male female
who you're dating whatever
in that sexual space i believe in that
moment
you are very much embodying an archetype
you could take a thousand of those cases
we could all share the case where we
were that person
and i guarantee we could through
correlation and through just
a perception through pattern recognition
recognize the qualities of an ideal man
or woman in that situation
that is something like an archetypal
hero and there's many that
that you can work with i i really enjoy
the amazing work by moore and gillette
king warrior magician and lover where he
in detail
analyzes and breaks down the shadow
sides the inner child and the
heroic aspects of king warrior magician
and lover and i think for women
it's the same as a quaternity you know i
call it queen priestess
huntress and um which one did i miss
lover as well so this is
this is really important to understand
if you are inclined to view the world
through an archetypal lens
which you might be inclined to view that
way if you really love
myth if you really love stories if you
really are attracted to
supernatural characters personality and
meaningful qualities and emotional
experiences not just
you know marvel superheroes although
that's dope and not just you know fairy
tales and arthurian myth although that's
a rich
place of lore but actual um
idea thought forms emotional energies
and integris thought indeed that
characterizes
what we what we think of as the best of
us right when you think of a human that
you would want to emulate
i believe these humans are to some small
degree
more aligned with these archetypes than
others
so i'll leave that there
okay um my notion of archetype is
that there are as kevin said
i studied anthropology in the first
place
culture and social anthropology there
are myths
and archetypes that you find all over
places times and cultures that
didn't have any contact to each other
you know so
there is a notion
they're not exactly overlapping like
they're not like one-on-one but they
have like
different notions if if you
if you're asking what i did is an
investigation it's like
the the archetypes tried to embrace like
wholeness
of the universe you know when we have it
more detailed
we have it in in horoscopes or in in
calendars and so on
that that have like a circular way of
seeing things
we have for example water and fire
as two opposing archetypes so that
we can find it ourselves with the fire
of a passion the fire of the anger
or the emotions of our tears and
in in the water or also in
in in depression or whatever so
there are like the ideas that we create
out of
our our stories out of our language
that is an ideal type as
a sad already that we're striving for
and this direction and we that we are
striving for to be the ideal one
the ideal is not the real so the ideal
is always
an idea that that leads us
so the archetype is also an idea that
leads us
to something something bigger because it
contains
multiplicities of ideas from what we
think about that
is to something that makes us
more beautiful more true more
more good somehow and
in in the in the distinction of
what kind of archetype we're striving
for
it is also our desire of what we want to
become
but how this becoming into the real
of your unique oneness
is displayed is not
the fixed idea but it becomes
the real of what you feel is ideal
for the reveal for you
so it has like the whole notion that can
drive you to to become a better person
to become a notion of or to become
someone
someone that is yeah
ideal and
one hand the the most
i think where it comes to also into
places where the ego kicks into the
place where you become
someone that thinks okay he is the king
and he is like actually backing and
stuff like that
is is very uh dangerous too
so one of the things that are quite
crucial in here is
is a humbleness in working with
with archetypes that you don't think
you're creating uh the king
inside of yourself and you're the only
one
everybody is a king everybody is a lover
and there is plenty of space for for
every
everyone's uniqueness you know i think
that that
is very crucial working with archetypes
and and when it comes to to the
from the multiplicity into where we say
okay we have for example
as kevin said four archetypes where we
say this is the year this is that
it is it comes to the nation where there
is only one
you know where we you become just the
one
that you are and that's where you're not
thriving anymore to be
something more ideal that you're not
and this is the end of archetypal
thinking
but as long as you you wish for
being something that you're not the
archetypes are really
really useful as long as you take a
humble path with it
thank you well we've got many questions
still
here um but we have come to 90 minutes
it might be prudent
to bring this to a close as
peter might say um do you guys have any
closing thoughts anything that you would
like to
end with um before we do and maybe one
day we can
bring it in for a round two sure
i think the thing that's being presenced
throughout a lot of the questions
a lot of the things that are being
presenced in the chat have to do with
this
paradox between the one and the
multiplicity
so the one on the one hand is this
desire for monogamy this desire for
long-term relationships this desire for
exclusivity this desire for closeness
and intimacy with
one other and on the other hand there's
this desire for multiplicity which is a
desire to explore identity
and a desire to go into difference a
desire to
you know play with identity in a
different way to be
untethered from historical constraints
and so forth
and i just think i just think that the
way in my
personal life i have come to deal with
this paradox between the one and the
multiplicity
is that if you go too strongly into the
one
you become almost static and fixed in
your identity
to the point where neither you or the
other can change
and that becomes paralyzing and if you
go too much in the multiplicity
you go to the point where you're kind of
like schizophrenic and fragmented and
disconnected and
and you're spread out over too many
places
and somehow somehow we have to be able
to cultivate nuance with our sexual
energy
and build long-term meaningful
relationships with others whether we're
sexual or not with them
and at the same time leave space for
exploration
how to do that in my view is going to be
unique to every individual
but the path of extreme oneness
and the path of extreme multiplicity are
both dead ends
so it has to be some sort of dynamical
balancing
of of oneness and that's going to be
different to every person and i think
it's different on a developmental
trajectory
meaning that it's going to be different
at 20 than it is at 30 than it is at 40
than it is at 50.
um so i think that's that's been
presenced a lot and i just wanted to
speak to that because i think
metaphysically it's actually hard to
language this this this balance
that's that's all i have to say thank
you so much everyone thank you so much
for listening this is
all your questions all this chat man i
am so
overwhelmed this has been really cool so
thank you guys
yeah really really grateful for this
opportunity tyson love you brother thank
you so much for
sharing this with us and and inviting us
on here you know i i think
the biggest takeaway is that while being
in a in a dialogue and a discussion like
this
with people that are very deep thinkers
and are putting some heavy
things on the line like heavy in a good
way is really refreshing
um that's one two i think
clearly that we all are desiring in our
own way
to attain clarity and mastery around
communal living in the sexual space
and that that is pretty clear from a lot
of these questions and i think that's
incredible because that is at the
leading edge of
what i think a lot of us want to do
smart villages eco villages whether you
actually want to live in them or you
want to be part of a digital commons
i mean this is what it's all about i
think as we move forward so i'm excited
to continue that conversation and
you know if for some reason it's not
clear
if you love this you'll love the book so
sex masculinity god.com
um i humbly ask for amazon reviews if
you really dig it
help us get it out there we're going to
be launching a kindle version as well
potentially even an audiobook version in
the future if that's more your bag
but right now the paperback is amazing
it's our baby and
we're excited to share with you so
thanks y'all
yes thank you all for these amazing
questions
for holding that space tyson wonderful
conversations in here
i love this this structure of the
trilogy i
really can uh recommend it
the final remarks that i have to kind of
uh
they should do the counterpart together
about the oneness and the multiplicity
i do believe that both is not at that
end maybe it is at that end
but it is it is an end of
of of the evolution that is when you can
stay in the
multiplicity by being one and seeing
the multiplicity as each being the one
and as long as you see yourself as
as there is there is another is
as something foreign to you that
that is not a one as well as you're the
one
you know as long as that is the case
there is the potential for growth as
long as you see
there is there is something that is
other there is a person that is other
that is not you as long as that
coexists with the notion that
we we are all the other person
and i truly recom i truly experienced
that
and not to everyone otherwise
i don't know what i would be but i do
believe that
everything that you feel like an other
should really
um give you the power to say
oh that's my learning challenge
everybody that really is so makes you
angry or makes you
sad or whatever it's like this is
this is another one that is me
you know what does it teach me if i
don't feel it that
that is something that is just for me so
i do see that that this is like the the
pathway to go
you know and that fills me hope and that
fills me also
with uh with the direction that i have
been always following my life
with all the changes around you know
that is like the
the stable ground where where see
see development in humankind and in
myself
and yes if you leave some comment on
amazon
wonderful that would help us to get a
better out and have proper conversations
like this
i loved it thank you all it was really
amazing
talk to you all terrific thank you so
much for being here
this has been awesome i'm going to make
just a couple announcements here
um of course go to the stoa.ca to see
future events
on october 3rd we've got a bioenergetic
workout i'm speaking that one because i
think
just because i think kevin would be
intrigued by that um
and on november 16th noam chomsky's
going to be here so
peter's doing a great job with the stoa
and bringing in a lot of interesting
people
so if you would like to support peter
and the stoa
you can go to that patreon link give him
that support
the link for the book sex masculinity
and god
is there again so do order the book and
leave a review
and i dropped one more link to flowing
with unknowingness which is an event
that i host
every monday at 8 30 pm eastern time
where we practice freestyle freestyle
rap and spoken word as a way of getting
into communitas and deepening our
relationship with uncertainty
so thank you everybody for being here i
look forward to
seeing you again next time
thanks again everyone soon